<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[Typebar]]></title>
  <link href="http://typebar.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://typebar.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-19T11:46:44+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://typebar.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Pedro && Anton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Maze of a thousand parts]]></title>
    <link href="http://typebar.github.io/blog/2014/02/18/maze-of-a-thousand-parts/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-18T10:43:20+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://typebar.github.io/blog/2014/02/18/maze-of-a-thousand-parts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After a lengthy morning of flipping through data sheets and weighing
our options, we have placed an order with Farnell to get the initial
parts needed to begin prototyping Typebar.</p>

<p>With multiplexers, shift registers, rotary encoders, RGB LEDs, reed
switches, prototyping PCBs galore, we are high spirits, hoping that we
didn&rsquo;t leave anything vital off our list.</p>

<p>We have also acquired a Bluetooth board base around the BlueGiga BLE112
Bluetooth Smart Module.</p>

<p>With the delivery gnomes packing, racking, and clacking our parts over
to us, we will be programming a few libraries to manage the Bluetooth
communication and flip flopping of the typewriter keys.</p>

<p>One of the most essential parts is a blue tooth capable board that will
help the user to have a convenient way of accessing their typed data. While
we wait on the order which will be here within 24 hours we can start
looking at all that code. It&rsquo;s time to build a few libraries to help
navigate the mappings required for all 47 keys as well as other switches
and LEDs too.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Typewriter found]]></title>
    <link href="http://typebar.github.io/blog/2014/02/16/typewriter-found/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-16T10:42:32+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://typebar.github.io/blog/2014/02/16/typewriter-found</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We have finally collected our typewriter and overall it is in very
good condition. Despite a few sticky keys and a slightly tired looking
ribbon it is a bargain for £15 and with a little bit of maintenance we
should have her sorted out in no time.</p>

<p>The seller of typewriter, Rob Parrett, a music producer and
self-proclaimed &ldquo;car boot&rdquo; enthusiast,  has a fantastic collection of
instruments and oddities from his many years of collecting.</p>

<p>The first and arguably most important stage of our journey is
complete, as now we have a Royal Typewriter to cut, and configure into
a new fandangled contraption, with all the modern convenience of a 21st
century typing gizmo.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Hunt]]></title>
    <link href="http://typebar.github.io/blog/2014/02/10/the-hunt/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-10T10:43:37+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://typebar.github.io/blog/2014/02/10/the-hunt</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Rain trickled off the tent roofs of cramped rows stalls and miniature
shops as we walked through Camden Lock Market. A sprawling market in
East London, Camden Lock Market is home to the eclectic and oddity
filled world of second-hand goods, and for that reason, we found
ourselves wading into a labyrinth of tight corridors and make-shift
alleyways on a hunt.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://typebar.github.io/images/IMG_0997.jpg" style="width: auto;
height: 420px;" alt="Lock Market"></p>

<p>Our hunt began with the decision to try, on what one may consider the
most miserable of rainy days, to find an old typewriter to tear apart
and rebuild with a new circulatory system of wires and electrical
confabulations. Much like the typewriters we where in search of, the
market had traded in its golden buttons and knobs for an infinite
amount of character from years of constant use.</p>

<p>Search through the rows of stalls we happened upon a small shop, if
you could call it a shop as it was more of a cutout corner of a
warehouse, which was divided up into small shops with borders created
from the mass of nick-knacks the shopkeepers had accumulated.</p>

<p>An average sized, circularly bespectacled man, who lack follicular
fortitude approached us as we lazily strolled past his shop. &ldquo;Can I
help,&rdquo; he inquired. We regained him with the details of our
typewritered quest, and to our great remiss he informed us that not
only the item we searched for was rare but that the one stall he could
think of that might sell such an item was closed on this unfortunately
dreary Monday.</p>

<p>Sighing in frustration we concede to not be beaten by lock market so
easily and to press on in our search of the item we most desired in
the world &ndash; a tiny, but tasteful typewriter, or two.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://typebar.github.io/images/IMG_0998.jpg" style="width: 420px;
height: auto;" alt="Photo Typewriter"></p>

<p>We came upon an uber trendy photography shop with a beautiful old
typewriter on display though not for sale. The sales guy kindly let us
have a play with the mechanisms and we quickly saw many potential
parts to attach various sensors too. Another half hour or so of
wandering brought us back to a small shop we had not noticed on our
first circuit.</p>

<p>Near the main entrance of the market, a small shop selling notebooks,
and random cards with inspirational sayings on them, had two little
typewriters for sale.</p>

<p>Typewriter one, for £70, was beaten-up and had quite a few sticky
keys, which was most likely due to the fact that as the shop keeper
told us, &ldquo;WD40 works to unstick the keys&rdquo; (Note: WD40 is great for
removing dirt and residue, but something like Hoppe&rsquo;s Gun Oil is
needed to lubricate a typewriter).</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://typebar.github.io/images/IMG_0999.jpg" style="width: 420px;
height: auto;" alt="Typewriter"></p>

<p>Tucked away behind a few boxes, the shop keeper had another more
modern, Olympic brand typewriter. This low profile, sleek white
machine, although in better condition then the first typewriter, still
needed a lot of TLC.</p>

<p>We decided to leave these two typing companions in need of a better
home, and continue our search elsewhere (eBay and gumtree being our
most hopeful candidates).</p>

<p>On our travels back, I (Pedro) decided to ring a friend. Rob Parrett,
a music producer and collector extraordinaire, had a lovely little
machine in full working order, that he said we could take off his
hands for the reasonable price of £15.</p>

<p>Although the moth-balled rows of Camden Lock Market didn&rsquo;t present us
with a beautiful blue Smith Corona, we feel as though we have come out
ahead having seen three different types of typewriters, and found out
that sometimes calling your friends before you go trudge through a
clutter market might just be your very best option.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hello, Typebar!]]></title>
    <link href="http://typebar.github.io/blog/2014/02/07/hello-typebar/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-07T13:11:49+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://typebar.github.io/blog/2014/02/07/hello-typebar</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We like typewriters and hope you do too! That&rsquo;s why we started <a href="http://typebar.github.io/">Typebar</a>, an open-source project designed to allow the quick and easy re-purposing of vintage typewriters.</p>

<p>Through examples, source-code, and tutorials, we hope to help you on your way to recycling your old typing pal.</p>

<p>The project is currently at the planning stage, but we hope to share every bit of our journey with you along the way.</p>

<p>We are sourcing a couple of typewriters to disassemble and modify with some nifty switches and LEDs, so check back soon for some glam shots of rusty old, character filled, typing companions.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
