<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: general | Typebar]]></title>
  <link href="http://typebar.github.io/blog/categories/general/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://typebar.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-26T17:43:44+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://typebar.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Pedro && Anton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Maze of a thousand parts]]></title>
    <link href="http://typebar.github.io/blog/2014/02/18/maze-of-a-thousand-parts/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-18T10:43:20+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://typebar.github.io/blog/2014/02/18/maze-of-a-thousand-parts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After a lengthy morning of flipping through data sheets and weighing
our options, we have placed an order with Farnell to get the initial
parts needed to begin prototyping Typebar.</p>

<p>With multiplexers, shift registers, rotary encoders, RGB LEDs, reed
switches, prototyping PCBs galore, we are high spirits, hoping that we
didn&rsquo;t leave anything vital off our list.</p>

<p>We have also acquired a Bluetooth board base around the BlueGiga BLE112
Bluetooth Smart Module.</p>

<p>With the delivery gnomes packing, racking, and clacking our parts over
to us, we will be programming a few libraries to manage the Bluetooth
communication and flip flopping of the typewriter keys.</p>

<p>One of the most essential parts is a blue tooth capable board that will
help the user to have a convenient way of accessing their typed data. While
we wait on the order which will be here within 24 hours we can start
looking at all that code. It&rsquo;s time to build a few libraries to help
navigate the mappings required for all 47 keys as well as other switches
and LEDs too.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Typewriter found]]></title>
    <link href="http://typebar.github.io/blog/2014/02/16/typewriter-found/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-16T10:42:32+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://typebar.github.io/blog/2014/02/16/typewriter-found</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We have finally collected our typewriter and overall it is in very
good condition. Despite a few sticky keys and a slightly tired looking
ribbon it is a bargain for £15 and with a little bit of maintenance we
should have her sorted out in no time.</p>

<p>The seller of typewriter, Rob Parrett, a music producer and
self-proclaimed &ldquo;car boot&rdquo; enthusiast,  has a fantastic collection of
instruments and oddities from his many years of collecting.</p>

<p>The first and arguably most important stage of our journey is
complete, as now we have a Royal Typewriter to cut, and configure into
a new fandangled contraption, with all the modern convenience of a 21st
century typing gizmo.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
